11 chapter 12 of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public
domain Black Beauty by Anna suul chapter 12 A Stormy
Day One day late in the autumn my master had a long journey to go on business. I
was put into the dog cart and John went with his
master. I always liked to go in the dog cart it was so light and the high wheels
ran along so pleasantly. There had been a great deal of rain and and now the wind
was very high and blew the dry leaves across the road in a shower. We went
along merrily till we came to the tollbar and the low wooden bridge. The
river banks were rather high, and the bridge, instead of rising, went across
just level, so that in the middle, if the river was full, the water would be nearly
up to the woodwork and planks; but as there were good substantial rails on
each side, people did not mind it. The man at the gate said the river
was rising in fast, and he feared it would be a bad night. Many of the meadows
were underwater and in one low part of the road the water was halfway up to my
knees; the bottom was good, and master drove gently, so it was no
matter. When we got to the town of course I had a good bait, but as the master's
business engaged him a long time we did not start for home until rather late in
the afternoon. The wind was then much higher, and I heard the master say to
John that he had never been out in such a storm;
and so I thought, as we went along the skirts of a wood, where the great
branches were swaying about like twigs, and the rushing sound was
terrible. “I wish we were well out of this wood,” said my master. “Yes, sir,” said John, “it
would be rather awkward if one of these branches came down on
us.” The words were scarcely out of his mouth when there was a groan, and a crack,
and a splitting sound, and tearing, crashing down among the other trees came
an oak, torn up by the roots, and it fell right across the road just before
us. I will never say I was not frightened, for I was. I stopped still, and I believe
I trembled; of course I did not turn around or run away; I was not brought up
to that Jon jumped out and was in a moment at my head. “That was a very near
touch,” said my master. “What's to be done now?” “Well, sir, we can't drive over that
tree, nor yet get round it; there will be nothing for it, but to go back to the
four crossways, and that will be a good 6 miles before we get around the wooden
bridge again; it will make us late, but the horse is fresh.” So back we went and
round by the crossroads, but by the time we got to the bridge it was very nearly
dark; we could just see that the water was over the middle of it; but as that
happened sometimes when the floods were out, master did not stop. We were going
along at a good pace, but the moment my feet touched the first part of the
bridge I felt sure there was something wrong. I dare not go forward, and I made a dead
stop. “Go on, Beauty,” said my master, and he
gave me a touch with the whip, but I dare
not stir; he gave me a sharp cut; I jumped, but I dare not go
forward. “There's something wrong, sir,” said John, and he sprang out of the dog cart
and came to my head and looked all about.
He tried to lead me forward. “Come on, Beauty, what's the
matter?” Of course I could not tell him, but I knew very well that the bridge was not
safe. Just then the man at the Tollgate on the other side ran out of the house,
tossing a torch about like one mad. “Hoy, hoy, hoy Hue stop!” he cried. “What's the
matter?” shouted my master. “The bridge is broken in the middle, and part of it is
carried away; if you come on you'll be into the river.” “Thank God!” said my master. “You
Beauty!” said johon and took the bridle and gently turned me round to the right
hand road by the Riverside The sun had set some time; the
wind seemed to have lulled off since that furious blast which tore up the
tree. It grew darker and darker, stiller and stiller. I trotted quietly along, the
wheels hardly making a sound on a soft road. For a good while neither master nor JN spoke,
and then master began in a serious voice. I could not understand much of
what they said, but I found they thought, if I had gone on as the master wanted me,
most likely the bridge would have given way under us, and horse Chas master, and
man would have fallen into the river; and as the current was flowing very strongly,
and there was no light and no help at hand, it was more than likely we should
all have been drowned. Master said, God had given men reason by by which they could find out
things for themselves; but he had given animals knowledge which did not depend
on reason, and which was much more prompt and perfect in its way, and by which they
had often saved the lives of men. John had many stories to tell of
dogs and horses, and the wonderful things they had done; he thought people did not
value their animals half enough nor make friends of them as they ought to do. I am
sure he makes friends of them if ever a man
did. At last we came to the gates and found the gardener looking out for us. He
said the mistress had been in a dreadful way ever since dark, fearing some
accident had happened, and that she had sent James off on Justice, the rone cob,
toward the wooden bridge to make inquiry after us. We saw a light at the hall door
and at the upper windows, and as we came up mistress ran out, saying, “Are you
really safe, my dear? Oh I've been so anxious, fancying all sorts of things.
Have you had no accident?” “No, my dear; but if your Black Beauty had
not been wiser than we were we should all have been carried down the river at the wooden
bridge.” I heard no more, as they went into the house, and John took me to the stable.
Oh, what a good supper he gave me that night, a good bran mash and some crushed
beans with my oats, and such a thick bed
of straw! and I was glad of it, for I was tired end of chapter 12